Let me show you something.
To be precise,
I'm going to show you nothing.
This was the world 540 million years ago.
Pure, endless darkness.
It wasn't dark due to a lack of light.
It was dark because of a lack of sight.
Although sunshine did filter 1,000 meters
beneath the surface of ocean,
a light permeated from hydrothermal
vents to seafloor,
brimming with life,
there was not a single eye
to be found in these ancient waters.
No retinas, no corneas, no lenses.
So all this light,
all this life went unseen.
There was a time that the very idea
of seeing didn't exist.
It [had] simply never been done before.
Until it was.
So for reasons we're only
beginning to understand,
trilobites, the first organisms
that could sense light, emerged.
They're the first inhabitants
of this reality that we take for granted.
First to discover that there is
something other than oneself.
A world of many selves.
The ability to see is thought
to have ushered in Cambrian explosion,
a period in which a huge
variety of animal species
entered fossil records.
What began as a passive experience,
the simple act of letting light in,
soon became far more active.
The nervous system began to evolve.
Sight turning to insight.
Seeing became understanding.
Understanding led to actions.
And all these gave rise to intelligence.
Today, we're no longer satisfied with just
nature's gift of visual intelligence.
Curiosity urges us to create machines
to see just as intelligently as we can,
if not better.
Nine years ago, on this stage,
I delivered an early progress report
on computer vision,
a subfield of artificial intelligence.
Three powerful forces
converged for the first time.
Aa family of algorithms
called neural networks.
Fast, specialized hardware
called graphic processing units,
or GPUs.
And big data.
Like the 15 million images that my lab
spent years curating called ImageNet.
Together, they ushered in
the age of modern AI.
We've come a long way.
Back then, just putting labels on images
was a big breakthrough.
But the speed and accuracy
of these algorithms just improved rapidly.
The annual ImageNet
challenge, led by my lab,
gauged the performance of this progress.
And on this plot, you're seeing
the annual improvement
and milestone models.
We went a step further
and created algorithms
that can segment objects
or predict the dynamic
relationships among them
in these works done by my students
and collaborators.
And there's more.
Recall last time I showed you
the first computer-vision algorithm
that can describe a photo
in human natural language.
That was work done with my brilliant
former student, Andrej Karpathy.
At that time, I pushed my luck and said,
"Andrej, can we make computers
to do the reverse?"
And Andrej said,
"Ha ha, that's impossible."
Well, as you can see from this post,
recently the impossible
has become possible.
That's thanks to a family
of diffusion models
that powers today's
generative AI algorithm,
which can take human-prompted sentences
and turn them into photos and videos
of something that's entirely new.
Many of you have seen the recent
impressive results of Sora by OpenAI.
But even without the enormous
number of GPUs,
my student and our collaborators
have developed a generative
video model called Walt
months before Sora.
And you're seeing some of these results.
There is room for improvement.
I mean, look at that cat's eye
and the way it goes under the wave
without ever getting wet.
What a cat-astrophe.
(Laughter)
And if past is prologue,
we will learn from these mistakes
and create a future we imagine.
And in this future,
we want AI to do everything it can for us,
or to help us.
For years I have been saying
that taking a picture is not the same
as seeing and understanding.
Today, I would like to add to that.
Simply seeing is not enough.
Seeing is for doing and learning.
When we act upon this world
in 3D space and time,
we learn, and we learn
to see and do better.
Nature has created this virtuous cycle
of seeing and doing
powered by “spatial intelligence.”
To illustrate to you what your spatial
intelligence is doing constantly,
look at this picture.
Raise your hand if you feel
like you want to do something.
(Laughter)
In the last split of a second,
your brain looked
at the geometry of this glass,
its place in 3D space,
its relationship with the table, the cat
and everything else.
And you can predict
what's going to happen next.
The urge to act is innate to all beings
with spatial intelligence,
which links perception with action.
And if we want to advance AI
beyond its current capabilities,
we want more than AI
that can see and talk.
We want AI that can do.
Indeed, we're making exciting progress.
The recent milestones
in spatial intelligence
is teaching computers to see, learn, do
and learn to see and do better.
This is not easy.
It took nature millions of years
to evolve spatial intelligence,
which depends on the eye taking light,
project 2D images on the retina
and the brain to translate
these data into 3D information.
Only recently, a group
of researchers from Google
are able to develop an algorithm
to take a bunch of photos
and translate that into 3D space,
like the examples we're showing here.
My student and our collaborators
have taken a step further
and created an algorithm
that takes one input image
and turn that into 3D shape.
Here are more examples.
Recall, we talked about computer programs
that can take a human sentence
and turn it into videos.
A group of researchers
in University of Michigan
have figured out a way to translate
that line of sentence
into 3D room layout, like shown here.
And my colleagues at Stanford
and their students
have developed an algorithm
that takes one image
and generates infinitely plausible spaces
for viewers to explore.
These are prototypes of the first
budding signs of a future possibility.
One in which the human race
can take our entire world
and translate it into digital forms
and model the richness and nuances.
What nature did to us implicitly
in our individual minds,
spatial intelligence
technology can hope to do
for our collective consciousness.
As the progress of spatial
intelligence accelerates,
a new era in this virtuous cycle
is taking place in front of our eyes.
This back and forth
is catalyzing robotic learning,
a key component for any
embodied intelligence system
that needs to understand
and interact with the 3D world.
A decade ago,
ImageNet from my lab
enabled a database of millions
of high-quality photos
to help train computers to see.
Today, we're doing the same
with behaviors and actions
to train computers and robots
how to act in the 3D world.
But instead of collecting static images,
we develop simulation environments
powered by 3D spatial models
so that the computers can have
infinite varieties of possibilities
to learn to act.
And you're just seeing
a small number of examples
to teach our robots
in a project led by my lab
called Behavior.
We’re also making exciting progress
in robotic language intelligence.
Using large language model-based input,
my students and our collaborators
are among the first teams
that can show a robotic arm
performing a variety of tasks
based on verbal instructions,
like opening this drawer
or unplugging a charged phone.
Or making sandwiches,
using bread, lettuce, tomatoes
and even putting a napkin for the user.
Typically I would like
a little more for my sandwich,
but this is a good start.
(Laughter)
In that primordial ocean,
in our ancient times,
the ability to see and perceive
one's environment
kicked off the Cambrian explosion
of interactions with other life forms.
Today, that light
is reaching the digital minds.
Spatial intelligence is allowing machines
to interact not only with one another,
but with humans, and with 3D worlds,
real or virtual.
And as that future is taking shape,
it will have a profound
impact to many lives.
Let's take health care as an example.
For the past decade,
my lab has been taking
some of the first steps
in applying AI to tackle challenges
that impact patient outcome
and medical staff burnout.
Together with our collaborators
from Stanford School of Medicine
and partnering hospitals,
we're piloting smart sensors
that can detect clinicians
going into patient rooms
without properly washing their hands.
Or keep track of surgical instruments.
Or alert care teams when
a patient is at physical risk,
such as falling.
We consider these techniques
a form of ambient intelligence,
like extra pairs of eyes
that do make a difference.
But I would like more interactive help
for our patients, clinicians
and caretakers, who desperately
also need an extra pair of hands.
Imagine an autonomous robot
transporting medical supplies
while caretakers focus on our patients
or augmented reality,
guiding surgeons to do safer, faster
and less invasive operations.
Or imagine patients with severe paralysis
controlling robots with their thoughts.
That's right, brainwaves,
to perform everyday tasks
that you and I take for granted.
You're seeing a glimpse of that future
in this pilot study from my lab recently.
In this video, the robotic arm is cooking
a Japanese sukiyaki meal
controlled only by the brain
electrical signal,
non-invasively collected
through an EEG cap.
(Applause)
Thank you.
The emergence of vision
half a billion years ago
turned a world of darkness upside down.
It set off the most profound
evolutionary process:
the development of intelligence
in the animal world.
AI's breathtaking progress
in the last decade is just as astounding.
But I believe the full potential
of this digital Cambrian explosion
won't be fully realized until we power
our computers and robots
with spatial intelligence,
just like what nature did to all of us.
It’s an exciting time to teach
our digital companion
to learn to reason
and to interact with this beautiful
3D space we call home,
and also create many more new worlds
that we can all explore.
To realize this future won't be easy.
It requires all of us
to take thoughtful steps
and develop technologies
that always put humans in the center.
But if we do this right,
the computers and robots
powered by spatial intelligence
will not only be useful tools
but also trusted partners
to enhance and augment
our productivity and humanity
while respecting our individual dignity
and lifting our collective prosperity.
What excites me the most in the future
is a future in which that AI
grows more perceptive,
insightful and spatially aware,
and they join us on our quest
to always pursue a better way
to make a better world.
Thank you.
(Applause)